then we have an opportunity to influence the amount of future climate change that we will need to adapt to. So we have a choice. We can either choose to start to take climate change seriously, and significantly cut and mitigate our greenhouse gas emissions, and then we will have to adapt to less of the climate change impacts in future. Alternatively, we can continue to really ignore the climate change problem. But if we do that, we are also choosing to adapt to very much more powerful climate impacts in future. And not only that. As people who live in countries with high per capita emissions, we're making that choice on behalf of others as well. But the choice that we don't have is a no climate change future. Over the last two decades, our government negotiators and policymakers have been coming together to discuss climate change, and they've been focused on avoiding a two-degree centigrade warming above pre-industrial levels. That's the temperature that's associated with dangerous impacts across a range of different indicators, to humans and to the environment. So two degrees centigrade constitutes dangerous climate change. But dangerous climate change can be subjective. So if we think about an extreme weather event that might happen in some part of the world, and if that happens in a part of the world where there is good infrastructure, where there are people that are well-insured and so on, then that impact can be disruptive. It can cause upset, it could cause cost. It could even cause some deaths. But if that exact same weather event happens in a part of the world where there is poor infrastructure, or where people are not well-insured, or they're not having good support networks, then that same climate change impact could be devastating. It could cause a significant loss of home, but it could also cause significant amounts of death. So this is a graph of the CO2 emissions at the left-hand side from fossil fuel and industry, and time from before the Industrial Revolution out towards the present day. And what's immediately striking about this is that emissions have been growing exponentially. If we focus in on a shorter period of time from 1950, we have established in 1988 the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, the Rio Earth Summit in 1992, then rolling on a few years, in 2009 we had the Copenhagen Accord,
entonces tenemos la oportunidad de influir en la cantidad de cambio climático futuro que vamos a necesitar para adaptarnos. Así que tenemos una elección. Podemos optar por empezar a tomar en serio el cambio climático, y mitigar y reducir significativamente las emisiones de gases de efecto invernadero, y luego tendremos que adaptarnos a los menores impactos climáticos futuros. O podemos seguir ignorando el problema del cambio climático. Pero si hacemos eso, también estamos escogiendo adaptarnos a impactos muchísimo más potente del clima en el futuro. Y no solo eso. Como personas que vivimos en países con altas emisiones per cápita, estamos haciendo la elección en nombre de los demás. Pero la elección de que no disponemos es de un futuro sin cambio climático. Durante las dos últimas décadas, nuestros negociadores del Gobierno y los políticos han estado reuniéndose para discutir el cambio climático, y han estado enfocados en evitar un calentamiento de 2 grados centígrados sobre los niveles preindustriales. Esa es la temperatura que está asociada con impactos peligrosos a través de una gama de diferentes indicadores, para los seres humanos y para el medio ambiente. Así que 2 grados centígrados constituyen un cambio climático peligroso. Pero el cambio peligroso puede ser subjetivo. Así que si pensamos en un evento extremo que podría suceder en alguna parte del mundo, y ocurre en una parte del mundo donde hay una buena infraestructura, donde hay personas que están bien aseguradas y así, entonces ese impacto puede ser perjudicial. Puede causar malestar, podría generar costos. Incluso algunas muertes. Pero si ese mismo evento pasa en una parte del mundo donde hay infraestructura deficiente, o donde las personas no están bien aseguradas, o no tienen buenas redes de apoyo, ese mismo impacto del cambio climático podría ser devastador. Podría causar una pérdida significativa de viviendas, y también podría causar cantidades significativas de muertos. Este es un gráfico de las emisiones de CO2 en el lado izquierdo a partir de combustibles fósiles y la industria, y el tiempo antes de la Revolución Industrial hasta el día de hoy. Y lo que inmediatamente llama la atención aquí es que las emisiones han crecido de manera exponencial. Si nos centramos en un período más corto, a partir de 1950, establecimos en 1988 el Grupo Intergubernamental de Expertos sobre el Cambio Climático, la Cumbre de la Tierra de Río en 1992, luego yendo unos pocos años, en 2009 tuvimos el Acuerdo de Copenhague,
where it established avoiding a two-degree temperature rise in keeping with the science and on the basis of equity. And then in 2012, we had the Rio+20 event. And all the way through, during all of these meetings and many others as well, emissions have continued to rise. And if we focus on our historical emission trend in recent years, and we put that together with our understanding of the direction of travel in our global economy, then we are much more on track for a four-degree centigrade global warming than we are for the two-degree centigrade. Now, let's just pause for a moment and think about this four-degree global average temperature. Most of our planet is actually made up of the sea. Now, because the sea has a greater thermal inertia than the land, the average temperatures over land are actually going to be higher than they are over the sea. The second thing is that we as human beings don't experience global average temperatures. We experience hot days, cold days, rainy days, especially if you live in Manchester like me. So now put yourself in a city center. Imagine somewhere in the world: Mumbai, Beijing, New York, London. It's the hottest day that you've ever experienced. There's sun beating down, there's concrete and glass all around you. Now imagine that same day -- but it's six, eight, maybe 10 to 12 degrees warmer on that day during that heat wave. That's the kind of thing we're going to experience under a four-degree global average temperature scenario. And the problem with these extremes, and not just the temperature extremes, but also the extremes in terms of storms and other climate impacts, is our infrastructure is just not set up to deal with these sorts of events. So our roads and our rail networks have been designed to last for a long time and withstand only certain amounts of impacts in different parts of the world. And this is going to be extremely challenged. Our power stations are expected to be cooled by water to a certain temperature to remain effective and resilient. And our buildings are designed to be comfortable within a particular temperature range. And this is all going to be significantly challenged under a four-degree-type scenario. Our infrastructure has not been designed to cope with this. So if we go back, also thinking about four degrees, it's not just the direct impacts, but also some indirect impacts. So if we take food security, for example. Maize and wheat yields in some parts of the world are expected to be up to 40 percent lower under a four-degree scenario, rice up to 30 percent lower. This will be absolutely devastating for global food security. So all in all, the kinds of impacts anticipated under this four-degree centigrade scenario
donde se estableció evitar un aumento de temperatura de 2 grados en consonancia con la ciencia y sobre la base de la equidad. Y luego, en 2012, tuvimos el evento Río + 20. Y todo este camino, durante todas estas reuniones y muchas otras más, y las emisiones han seguido aumentando. Si nos centramos en la tendencia histórica de emisiones en los últimos años, y ponemos que junto a nuestra comprensión del sentido de la marcha en nuestra economía global, entonces estamos mucho más en el camino para un cambio de 4 grados centígrados del calentamiento global de lo que estamos para el de 2 grados centígrados. Vamos a hacer una pausa un momento y pensar en esto de 4 grados en la temperatura media global. La mayor parte de nuestro planeta es en realidad mar. Debido a que el mar tiene una mayor inercia térmica que la tierra, las temperaturas medias por la tierra son en realidad mayores que las del mar. La segunda cosa es que como seres humanos no experimentamos las temperaturas medias globales. Experimentamos los días de calor, los días fríos, los días de lluvia, sobre todo si viven en Manchester como yo. Pónganse en el centro de la ciudad. Imaginen un lugar en el mundo: Mumbai, Pekín, Nueva York, Londres. Es el día más caluroso que alguna vez han experimentado. El sol caía hay concreto y cristal a su alrededor. Ahora imaginen que ese mismo día, pero 6, 8 o tal vez de 10 a 12 grados más caliente en ese día durante la ola de calor. Ese es el tipo de cosas que vamos a experimentar en un escenario de la temperatura media global de 4 grados. Y el problema con estos extremos, y no solo con las temperaturas extremas, sino también los extremos en términos de tormentas y otros impactos climáticos, es que nuestra infraestructura simplemente no se creó para enfrentar estos eventos. Nuestros caminos y redes ferroviarias han sido diseñados para durar largo tiempo y soportar solo ciertos impactos en diferentes partes del mundo. Y esto va a ser muy retado. Se espera que nuestros centrales eléctricas sean enfriadas con agua a una temperatura determinada para seguir siendo eficaces y resistentes. Nuestros edificios están diseñados para ser cómodos dentro de un intervalo de temperatura. Y todo esto va a ser cuestionado de manera significativa bajo un escenario de tipo de 4 grados. Nuestra infraestructura no ha sido diseñada para hacer frente a esto. Remontémonos, también pensando en unos cuatro grados, no son solo en los impactos directos, sino también algunos impactos indirectos. Si tomamos la seguridad alimentaria, por ejemplo. Los rendimientos del maíz y el trigo en algunas partes del mundo se espera que sean hasta un 40 % más bajos en un escenario de 4 grados, arroz hasta un 30 % menor. Esto será absolutamente devastador para la seguridad alimentaria mundial. Así que en general, los tipos de impactos anticipados bajo este escenario de 4 grados centígrados
are going to be incompatible with global organized living. So back to our trajectories and our graphs of four degrees and two degrees. Is it reasonable still to focus on the two-degree path? There are quite a lot of my colleagues and other scientists who would say that it's now too late to avoid a two-degree warming. But I would just like to draw on my own research on energy systems, on food systems, aviation and also shipping, just to say that I think there is still a small fighting chance of avoiding this two-degree dangerous climate change. But we really need to get to grips with the numbers to work out how to do it. So if you focus in on this trajectory and these graphs, the yellow circle there highlights that the departure from the red four-degree pathway to the two-degree green pathway is immediate. And that's because of cumulative emissions, or the carbon budget. So in other words, because of the lights and the projectors that are on in this room right now, the CO2 that is going into our atmosphere as a result of that electricity consumption lasts a very long time. Some of it will be in our atmosphere for a century, maybe much longer. It will accumulate, and greenhouse gases tend to be cumulative. And that tells us something about these trajectories. First of all, it tells us that it's the area under these curves that matter, not where we reach at a particular date in future. And that's important, because it doesn't matter if we come up with some amazing whiz-bang technology to sort out our energy problem on the last day of 2049, just in the nick of time to sort things out. Because in the meantime, emissions will have accumulated. So if we continue on this red, four-degree centigrade scenario pathway, the longer we continue on it, that will need to be made up for in later years to keep the same carbon budget, to keep the same area under the curve, which means that that trajectory, the red one there, becomes steeper. So in other words, if we don't reduce emissions in the short to medium term, then we'll have to make more significant year-on-year emission reductions. We also know that we have to decarbonize our energy system. But if we don't start to cut emissions in the short to medium term, then we will have to do that even sooner. So this poses really big challenges for us. The other thing it does is tells us something about energy policy. If you live in a part of the world where per capita emissions are already high, it points us towards reducing energy demand. And that's because with all the will in the world, the large-scale engineering infrastructure that we need to roll out rapidly to decarbonize the supply side of our energy system is just simply not going to happen in time. So it doesn't matter whether we choose nuclear power or carbon capture and storage, upscale our biofuel production, or go for a much bigger roll-out of wind turbines and wave turbines. All of that will take time. So because it's the area under the curve that matters, we need to focus on energy efficiency, but also on energy conservation -- in other words, using less energy. And if we do that, that also means that as we continue to roll out the supply-side technology, we will have less of a job to do if we've actually managed to reduce our energy consumption, because we will then need less infrastructure on the supply side. Another issue that we really need to grapple with is the issue of well-being and equity. There are many parts of the world where the standard of living needs to rise. Bbut with energy systems currently reliant on fossil fuel, as those economies grow so will emissions. And now, if we're all constrained by the same amount of carbon budget, that means that if some parts of the world's emissions are needing to rise, then other parts of the world's emissions need to reduce.
van a ser incompatibles con la vida organizada global. De vuelta a nuestras trayectorias y nuestros gráficos de 4 grados y 2 grados. ¿Es razonable aún a concentrarse en el camino de los 2 grados? Hay bastantes de mis colegas y otros científicos que dirían que ya es muy tarde para evitar un calentamiento de 2 grados. Pero me gustaría dibujar mi propia investigación en sistemas de energía, en sistemas alimentarios, aviación y también navegación, solo para decir que creo que todavía hay una pequeña oportunidad de luchar de evitar el peligro de 2 grados de cambio climático. Pero necesitamos familiarizarnos con los números para encontrar cómo hacerlo. Si se centran en esta trayectoria y estos gráficos, el círculo amarillo allí destaca que la partida de la vía de 4 grados roja a vía verde de los 2 grados es inmediata. Y eso es debido a las emisiones acumulativas, o el presupuesto de carbono. En otras palabras, a causa de las luces y los proyectores que están en este salón ahora mismo, el CO2 que está yendo a nuestra atmósfera como resultado de que el consumo de electricidad dura un tiempo muy largo. Algunos estarán en nuestra atmósfera un siglo, tal vez mucho más tiempo. Se acumularán y los gases de efecto invernadero tienden a acumularse. Y eso nos dice algo acerca de estas trayectorias. En primer lugar, nos dice que es el área bajo estas curvas lo que importa, no donde se llega en una fecha determinada en el futuro. Y eso es importante, porque no importa si encontramos alguna increíble tecnología, ¡plum!, para solucionar nuestro problema energético el último día de 2049, justo a tiempo para arreglar las cosas. Porque mientras tanto, las emisiones se han acumulado. Así que si seguimos en esta roja, de 4 grados centígrados, cuanto más tiempo continuamos en ella, más tendrá que ser compensado en años posteriores para el mismo presupuesto de carbono, para tener la misma área bajo la curva, lo que significa que esa trayectoria, roja allí, se hace más pronunciada. En otras palabras, si no reducimos las emisiones en el corto y mediano plazo, vamos a tener que hacer reducciones más significativas de año en año. Sabemos que tenemos que descarbonizar nuestro sistema energético. Pero si no empezamos a reducir las emisiones en el corto y mediano plazo, entonces vamos a tener que hacer eso incluso antes. Así que esto plantea realmente grandes desafíos para nosotros. La otro es que nos dice algo acerca de la política energética. Si viven en una parte del mundo donde las emisiones per cápita ya son altas, nos orienta hacia la reducción de la demanda de energía. Y esto porque con toda la voluntad del mundo, la infraestructura de ingeniería a gran escala que tenemos que desplegar rápidamente para descarbonizar la oferta de nuestro sistema energético simplemente no va a darse a tiempo. Así que no importa si elegimos la energía nuclear o la captura y almacenamiento de carbono, aumentamos la producción de biocombustibles, o ir a un mayor despliegue de turbinas de viento y turbinas de onda. Todo eso llevará tiempo. Así que como es el área bajo la curva lo que importa, tenemos que centrarnos en la eficiencia energética, y también en la conservación de energía en otras palabras, el uso de menos energía. Y si lo hacemos, eso también significa que a medida que seguimos lanzando la tecnología de oferta, tendremos menos que hacer si no nos hemos arreglado para reducir nuestro consumo de energía, porque vamos a tener menos infraestructura en el lado de la oferta. Otro tema con el que realmente tenemos que lidiar con es el tema de bienestar y equidad. Hay muchas partes del mundo donde el nivel de vida tiene que subir. Pero con sistemas de energía de combustibles fósiles, a medida que crecen las economías también lo harán las emisiones. Si todos estamos limitados por el mismo presupuesto de carbono, entonces si en algunas partes del mundo están necesitando subir, entonces en otras partes las emisiones mundiales deben reducirse.
So that poses very significant challenges for wealthy nations. Because according to our research, if you're in a country where per capita emissions are really high -- so North America, Europe, Australia -- emissions reductions of the order of 10 percent per year, and starting immediately, will be required for a good chance of avoiding the two-degree target. Let me just put that into context. The economist Nicholas Stern said that emission reductions of more than one percent per year
Esto plantea retos muy importantes para los países ricos. Porque de acuerdo con nuestra investigación, si estás en un país donde las emisiones per cápita son muy altas, América del Norte, Europa, Australia, la reducción de emisiones del orden del 10 % al año, a partir de ahora son necesarias para tener buena oportunidad de evitar la meta de los 2 grados. Permítanme poner esto en contexto. El economista Nicholas Stern dijo que las reducciones de emisiones de más de 1 % por año
had only ever been associated with economic recession or upheaval.
solo se habían asociado siempre con recesión económica o agitación.
So this poses huge challenges for the issue of economic growth, because if we have our high carbon infrastructure in place, it means that if our economies grow, then so do our emissions. So I'd just like to take a quote from a paper by myself and Kevin Anderson back in 2011 where we said that to avoid the two-degree framing of dangerous climate change,
Así que esto plantea enormes desafíos para la tema del crecimiento económico, porque al tener nuestra infraestructura de alto carbono en su lugar, significa que si crecen nuestras economías, entonces también lo harán nuestras emisiones. Solo me gustaría citar un documento de Kevin Anderson y mío de 2011 donde dijimos que para evitar el el peligroso cambio de 2 grados,
economic growth needs to be exchanged at least temporarily for a period of planned austerity in wealthy nations. This is a really difficult message to take, because what it suggests is that we really need to do things differently. This is not about just incremental change. This is about doing things differently, about whole system change, and sometimes it's about doing less things. And this applies to all of us, whatever sphere of influence we have. So it could be from writing to our local politician to talking to our boss at work or being the boss at work, or talking with our friends and family, or, quite simply, changing our lifestyles. Because we really need to make significant change. At the moment, we're choosing a four-degree scenario. If we really want to avoid the two-degree scenario, there really is no time like the present to act. Thank you. (Applause) Bruno Giussani: Alice, basically what you're saying, the talk is, unless wealthy nations start cutting 10 percent per year the emissions now, this year, not in 2020 or '25, we are going to go straight to the four-plus-degree scenario. I am wondering what's your take on the cut by 70 percent for 2070. Alice Bows-Larkin: Yeah, it's just nowhere near enough to avoid two degrees. One of the things that often -- when there are these modeling studies that look at what we need to do, is they tend to hugely overestimate how quickly other countries in the world can start to reduce emissions. So they make kind of heroic assumptions about that. The more we do that, because it's the cumulative emissions, the short-term stuff that really matters. So it does make a huge difference. If a big country like China, for example, continues to grow even for just a few extra years, that will make a big difference to when we need to decarbonize. So I don't think we can even say when it will be, because it all depends on what we have to do in the short term. But I think we've just got huge scope, and we don't pull those levers that allow us to reduce the energy demand, which is a shame. BG: Alice, thank you for coming to TED and sharing this data. ABL: Thank you. (Applause)
el crecimiento económico tendría que ser cambiado al menos temporalmente por un período de austeridad en las naciones ricas. Este es un mensaje muy difícil de tomar, porque sugiere es que realmente tenemos que hacer las cosas de manera diferente. No es un cambio incremental. Se trata de hacer las cosas de manera diferente, cambiar todo el sistema, y, a veces se trata de hacer menos cosas. Y esto se aplica a todos nosotros, cualquiera que sea la esfera de influencia que tengamos. Podría ser escribir a nuestro político local hablar con nuestro jefe en el trabajo o ser el jefe en el trabajo, o hablar con amigos y familiares, o, simplemente, cambiar nuestro estilo de vida. Porque realmente tenemos que hacer un cambio significativo. Por el momento, estamos eligiendo un escenario de 4 grados. Si realmente queremos evitar el escenario de 2 grados, realmente no hay mejor momento que el presente para actuar. Gracias. (Aplausos) Bruno Giussani: Alice, lo que estás diciendo, es que a menos que los países ricos empiezan cortar el 10 % al año las emisiones ya, este año, no en 2020 o 25, vamos a ir directamente a la situación de más 4 grados. Me pregunto cuál es su opinión sobre el corte en un 70 % para 2070. Alice Bows-Larkin: Sí, es justo algo así para evitar 2 grados. Una de las cosas que a menudo... cuando hay estos estudios de modelos en que se ve lo que tenemos que hacer, se tiende a sobrestimar enormemente la rapidez con que otros países en el mundo pueden empezar a reducir las emisiones. Así hacen tipo de supuestos heroicos sobre eso. Cuanto más lo hacemos, porque son las emisiones acumuladas, el corto plazo es el que realmente importa. Hace una gran diferencia. Si un gran país como China, por ejemplo, sigue creciendo, incluso por unos pocos años más, hará una gran diferencia para cuando tengamos que descarbonizar. No creo que ni siquiera podamos decir cuándo va a ser, ya que depende de lo que tenemos que hacer en el corto plazo. Pero creo que tenemos gran alcance, y no tiramos de esas palancas que permitirán reducir la demanda de energía, lo que es una pena. BG: Alice, gracias por venir a TED y compartir estos datos. ABL: Gracias. (Aplausos)